<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A trumpet to call souldiers on to noble actions By the rare and new examples of two Christian kings and a prince, personally meeting in the open field of warre. Viz. Gustanus [sic] the now-present King of Sweden, against Sigismond King of Poland, and the Prince his sonne, in remouing of the siege of Meve, a towne in Poland, which was formerly gotten by the Sweden King, from the Poland. With many memorable stratagems and military occurrences attending on so honourable a designe. Sent out of Sweden, from a great man in the state, and written with his owne hand. Translated out of the Latine copie.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13982</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24295</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102475</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838258</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838258</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2631</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13982)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2631)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1086:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A trumpet to call souldiers on to noble actions By the rare and new examples of two Christian kings and a prince, personally meeting in the open field of warre. Viz. Gustanus [sic] the now-present King of Sweden, against Sigismond King of Poland, and the Prince his sonne, in remouing of the siege of Meve, a towne in Poland, which was formerly gotten by the Sweden King, from the Poland. With many memorable stratagems and military occurrences attending on so honourable a designe. Sent out of Sweden, from a great man in the state, and written with his owne hand. Translated out of the Latine copie.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By M. Flesher] for N. Bourne, and Tho: Archer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Swedish-Polish War, 1617-1629 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>[Gniew (Poland) --  Siege, 1617-1629] --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2631:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2631:1"/>
            <p>A TRVMPET TO CALL SOVL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIERS ON TO NOBLE ACTIONS.</p>
            <p>BY The rare and new Examples of two Chriſtian Kings and a Prince, perſonally meeting in the open field of warre.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Viz. Guſtanus</hi> the now-preſent King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and the Prince his ſonne, in remouing of the Siege of <hi>Meve,</hi> a Towne in <hi>Poland,</hi> which was formerly gotten by the <hi>Sweden</hi> King, from the <hi>Poland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With many memorable Stratagems and Military Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences attending on ſo honourable a Deſigne.</p>
            <p>Sent out of Sweden, from a great man in the State, and written with his owne hand.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the Latine Copie.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>N. Bourne,</hi> and <hi>Tho: Archer.</hi> 1627.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2631:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2631:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O ſee Kings and Princes ſweat in Battailes in theſe dayes, is ſo rare and vnuſuall, that this warlike En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter of <hi>Guſtanus</hi> the King of Sweden, with the King of Poland and his ſonne, is for the remarkabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of it, worthy to be engrauen in Tables of braſſe.</p>
            <p>The Prize for which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended was the Towne of Meve in Poland. The honour of the Aduenturer (the King of Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den) the more to be exalted, in that hee went out of his owne Court and Country (where hee liued in fulneſſe of all content) to trample on the fields and faces of his enemies, to beat at the Gates of the Polacke Cities, hunting after glory in a foraigne Kingdome, in despight of all the horrors which warre <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſeth to bring along with it: not regarding the petty Townes which he fought for, and did reſcue, but for the victory which ſhall crowne his fame to all eternitie.</p>
            <p>Here you ſhall ſee a braue young Gentleman, lay by all kingly regards of his owne life, and with eight thouſand Swedens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and fight with thirty thouſand Poles, and their adherents. The Polander hauing the aduantage of a hill, vpon which hee lay encamped and entrenched, and the Sweve ſpreading his handfull of an army beneath another hill.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:2631:3"/>
Here you may ſee this young King of Sweden, to fetch off à common Souldier, in his owne perſon, and to kill with his owne hands, that Polacke, who had ſet vpon the other.</p>
            <p>By which example of the Kings valour, the ſubiects vnder him, ran out like Lyons to the Battaile, and came off with a moſt glorious conqueſt: Glorious to their King, to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, to themſelues, and their poſteritie, and a diſhonour to the Enemy, being ſo many, to be driuen out of their owne fields by ſo few: ſome reporting that of the Poles and Coſſackes were ſlaine in this Battaile 5000 at leaſt.</p>
            <p>And albeit the truth of this great Action challengeth all Rites, Praiſes, and Acclamations to be giuen as due rewards to the Sweden (a ſtranger to vs) yet let not this ſtory (when it is read in after-times) be ſo ſpitefull as to bury the Name and Memory of the Engliſh Nation, honoured in the Darings and high deeds of Colonell <hi>Muſchampe</hi> (our Country-man) who behaued himſelfe nobly, manfully, and as a true-worthy Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier in all this ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Neyther muſt wee ſmother the high courage of that braue Bohemian <hi>Torne,</hi> whoſe warlike acts in this Enterpriſe, are his ſpeaking Chronicles: hee being after the King of Swedens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture home, left Generall in his ſtead.</p>
            <p>So Noble Souldiers, wiſhing you all no worſe fortune in your Battailes, nor no leſſe fame, than here the Sweves haue atchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, I leaue you to reade that which may ſerue as a patterne and preſident for all heroicall ſpirits to follow.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>So Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2631:3"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE RELATION OF the manner of the encamping and beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the towne of <hi>Meve</hi> by <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> King of Poland, and of the raiſing of the ſiege by <hi>Guſtanus</hi> King of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> had poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelfe of the Palatinate of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienburge,</hi> and by croſſing the riuer of Wyzel in <hi>Pommerellia,</hi> had incamped at <hi>Derſove,</hi> where he might with moſt ſafety and aduantage proceed in his Treaty of Neutrality with thoſe of <hi>Dantzicke:</hi> And (by ſome Forts caſt vp at <hi>Hovet</hi> and <hi>Derſove)</hi> to be more able to keepe the riuer fauourable and ſecure for ſtopping the attempts of the enemies.</p>
            <p>At length the King of Poland in perſon, with the Prince his ſonne, (accompanyed with a great part of the Poloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Nobility) marcheth with an army conſiſting of Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, thoſe of the Duchy of <hi>Spruce, Lituanians. Germanes,</hi> and <hi>Livonians,</hi> which he doth fortifie at <hi>Grudent,</hi> he paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the riuer, and commeth to <hi>Niewburghe,</hi> and from thence goeth on. And vpon the 7 of September 1626. he beſiegeth the towne of <hi>Meve,</hi> lying vpon the riuer of Wyzel: The towne hath a Caſtle compaſſed about with an old wall after the ancient manner of the townes in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many.</hi> The towne was diſtant foure miles from our Kings Campe, and was defended by a gariſon of 150 Swethen
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2631:4"/>
footmen, hauing 60 inhabitants ioyned with them. The Polonian (being encamped on the weſt ſide) makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe maſter of a hill, where there was a village, and there he doth ſtrongly entrench himſelfe, eſpecially in that place where the paſſage towards <hi>Meve</hi> did lye moſt open, and thereafter he beginnes to batter the towne with his ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the King of Sweden (knowing how vnable the place was to reſiſt the inuaſion of an aduiſed and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute enemy) did reſolue of nothing elſe, but that (he being ſhortned of time to enforce the raiſing of the ſiege) the towne would ſhortly bee rendred: the beſt encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments our King had depending either vpon an expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a ſcarcity of victuals, or other conueniences wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the enemies army might bee pinchod, or otherwiſe vpon the conſtancy and reſolution of the ſouldiers beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, who by defending themſelues valiantly, might giue ſome hope that the ſiege might bee prolonged<hi>:</hi> And to the end that neither the valour of the beſieged ſhould proue their ouerthrow, nor that the enemy ſhould attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute our Kings delay to feare, it was reſoluted that the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſhould diſlodge and encampe neerer the enemy and the towne.</p>
            <p>Vpon the 11 of September our King did remoue his Campe three miles neerer the enemy, and encampeth at <hi>Falkenow,</hi> where hee did prepare himſelfe with his army for ſome encounter, expecting that the enemy would offer ſome occaſion of ſeruice that day: Notwithſtanding the enemy did not ſtirre out of his quarter, but onely ſends forth eight troopes of Coſſackes, who did ouerrunne the fields about <hi>Falkenow:</hi> That day was ſpent in light skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes with Colonel <hi>Banneer,</hi> who was appointed for the guard of the point of an Iland where the two riuers of Wyzel and Noga<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t doe diuide themſelues.</p>
            <p>The place where our King did encampe, was betwixt the riuer of Wyzel and a great bank of earth or dyke lying
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2631:4"/>
over againſt the riuer: for the riuer hath a high and large dyke artificially raiſed for holding out the great land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>floods, whereby about the Spring time the country people doe ſuſtaine great loſſes: The King did make this high banke to ſerue for a trench, where at the further <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd of the quarter he did draw a ditch from the great dyke to the riuer, and thereby did fortifie his Campe.</p>
            <p>The next day being the 12 of September, our King (vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome conſultation had of the moſt expedient courſes for the reliefe of the towne) thought it neceſſary to make choice of ſome aduantageous place where he might haue the full view of all: And then he drawes forth 1000 horſe, with 2000 foot, and preſents himſelfe in full ſight of the enemy, hauing the riuer of Wyzel on his left, and the great dyke on his right hand: At length (aduancing forward for the ſpace of one halfe mile) he ſeeth the enemy drawing themſelues forth vpon the hill neere to their trenches where (there lying a plaine field betwixt both Campes) ſome few horſemen did enter in skirmiſh. There was not farre from thence a wood of oakes hauing groues of hazell wood on euery ſide, which did ſtretch it ſelfe to the hill poſſeſſed by the enemy, and to the riuer ſide.</p>
            <p>Our King being deſirous to ſee this wood, and to try whether the place would offer any good aduantage to force a paſſage to the hill or to the caſtle, did giue order that 500 muſquettiers, with 100 dragonnes ſhould be ſent forward: The King did follow himſelfe with 300 horſe, imagining that the enemy would march towards the wood with great forces: The King ſent for Colonell <hi>Muſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>champe,</hi> whom he commanded with 200 muſquettiers to put himſelfe in the way, if the enemy ſhould fall downe from the dyke. In the meane time the enemy had ſent the muſquettiers from the hill, and there after ſent fiue troops of Lanciers and Coſſackes: ſo that our foot-men skirmiſhing with the enemy, did force them to a retrait. It being vncertaine whethar this did proceed from the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2631:5"/>
cowardice or policie of the enemy, intending to draw on our men to ſome ambuſcadoe.</p>
            <p>Our foot aduancing too farre, were diſordered by the Polonian horſe, and ſome were killed. Not many of theſe had eſcaped, vnleſſe our King himſelfe (ſeeing one of his ſouldiers put hardly to it by one of the enemy) had not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced himſelfe for the reſcue of his ſouldier, and laid the Polonian dead vpon the ground. By which rare example his cauallery was much encouraged to giue on furiouſly vpon the enemy who were all beaten backe to the hill quiting the wood to our men, whilſt both the enemy and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ours were thus in fight, Colonell <hi>Muſchampe</hi> marched on to the foot of the hill neere the great dyke, where hee ſtayed the whole time of the ſeruice, not ſuffering the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to fall out any more in that quarter. The King did call for the reſt of the army, and that the Cannon ſhould bee brought in the wood within the great dyke, which when the Polonian did perceiue that the King did bend directly towards the wood, he ſends downe the greateſt part of his Infantery from the hill another way, that beating our men from thence he might be maſter thereof: And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all he ſends 20 troops of Lanciers and Coſſackes to lye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the great dyke and the hill in a plaine field, which was done as well to hold our King enuironed, as thereafter to fall vpon our troopes, which they thought could not be very ſtrong, and ſo by that meanes (as they did ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine) the warre might ſhortly be brought to an end.</p>
            <p>The enemies foot did cary themſelues well, ſtriuing for the Dyke with our men: Their Cauallerie did ſhow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vpon the plaine field, whereof ſome finding the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage nothing difficult, did leape ouer. In the meane time our King puts his armie in order, planting his Artillery in a place where the wood was thinneſt: hee commands 3 troopes of horſe to attend in the front neere the trench who ſhould be ready to attend the enemy, if they ſhould iſſue forth out of that quarter.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2631:5"/>
After that foure troupes of Lanciers had put themſelues in a groſſe ſquadron, to giue a charge, they ſeeing our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallery placed in the front, ready to abide their choake, they giue backes towards the plaine field, forſaking the great Dike: It was much debated whether this place were neceſſary to be maintayned, and whether the whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſhould be brought there: But when our forces being (howſoeuer) the weaker in numbers, were ſeparated, and that the ſouldiers were not provided of victuall, nor the horſe-men of forrage and other conveniences. It was concluded that the maine deſſigne ſhould not be altered, but that the forces there imployed ſhould march backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne to their old quarter, and thereafter to goe on reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely for the reliefe of the b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſiedged: The enemy was to bee remoued at what rate ſoeuer, who was lying ſtrong vpon the paſſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge towards <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Towne. The King giues order to his Marſhall of the field <hi>Herman Vrangle</hi> to draw forth of the Army foure Companies of foote, with two fielde peeces; the Marſhall was to giue on vppon the trenches: A<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter that the Artillery had played once or twice, and that ſome of our muſquettiers (by leaping o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the dike) had begun the charge, both horſe and foot did retire themſelues to the hill, quiting the great D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke: As the bri<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t did goe, there was killed of the enemies 150 a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom was the Captayne <hi>Deuhoffe</hi> with ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: So that they did retire to their Campe in that ſame order and way they came: The enemy looking on, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> adventuring further: There was ſome of ours woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and about 20. killed.</p>
            <p>The day following, our King (cauſing himſelfe to bee tranſported in a little Boate) did take a full view of the Iſlands of the river of <hi>Wizel,</hi> and of their approaches to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Towne, to the end that (before hee ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any further) hee might know the beſt advantages, how to enforce the rayſing of the ſiedge, or the moſt toyle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome difficulties to impeach the ſame.</p>
            <p>The King himſelfe approaches to the foote of the hill, having placed <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> muſquettiers vppon <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Duke.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2631:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Hee giveth 600. muſquettiers to the Count of <hi>Torne,</hi> and 500. <hi>Sweden</hi> foote to Colonell <hi>Muſtchamp:</hi> The one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing commanded to ſtay vpon the right hand, at the foote of the hill: The other at the left hand: both were ordered that they ſhould preſſe (by the ſteepneſſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and precipice of the hill) to keepe their men in greater ſafety, from the violence of the enemies ſh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t. The King commanded that neyther of them ſhould ſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rre without directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ſigne given: There was at the ſide of the VV<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od, a great precipice or ſteepneſſe planted with little Trees which covered thoſe that we<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e lying in ambuſcade, and h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lped alſo thoſe that were to giue the charge. There was a roade or path-way leading towards the hill, ſcarſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable for horſe-men, which path-way did lye betwixt Colonell <hi>Muſtchampe,</hi> and the Count of <hi>Torne.</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Muſtchamp</hi> was commanded to enter this path on horſe-backe, with ſome of his muſquettiers, that hee might learne what countenance the enemy kept on the hill, and to eſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye the beſt meanes hee could of beating them from thence. As the Colonell doth advance him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, hee is charged with a Troupe of <hi>Germaine</hi> horſe, and beaten backe to the road way: Some muſquettiers ſtrayning to deſengage their Colonell being killed, and ſome taken priſoners, the remainder did with-draw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the ſame way they went. But the nature of the place and paſſage being diſcovered, the Count of <hi>Torne</hi> and Colonell <hi>Muſtchampe</hi> doe charge reſolutely, and partly breaking through the roade way, and partly by the precipice of the hill at length they gayne the top there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: In the meane time, the enemy drawes all his forces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, the foot<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>-men from the qua<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter and forts, the horſe-men from the field, and charge our men forcibly to beate them from the top of the hill: The King and Prince of <hi>Poland</hi> beeing ſpectators: it was long foughten with much courage, eagerneſſe and noyſe: The <hi>Germain</hi> hor<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e-men beeing ſeconded by their foote and the <hi>Hayduckes,</hi> charge <hi>Muſtchampe</hi> but were repulſed with great loſſe.</p>
            <p>In the meane time out men lying diſcouered are beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2631:6"/>
with their Canon from their forts, neyther was there any thing left vnattempted, to make all our enterpriſe in-effectuall. At length, after two houres fighting, our men defending themſelues valiantly, and gayning ground of the enemy, ſome Troupes of the <hi>Polonian</hi> horſe, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciers, <hi>Caſſackes</hi> and <hi>Germaines</hi> mixed together (partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtricken with ſhame) partly being animated with the preſence of the King and Prince, promiſing rewards to the beſt deſervers, did furiouſly and in great diſorder charge the Count of <hi>Torne,</hi> who (perceiving what they intended) did make his Muſquettiers fall low on their knees, that nothi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g could bee ſeene but only their heads, whereby (the violence of the horſe-men being deluded) hee ſtood firme: Th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y beeing diſabled to follow their poynt in regard of the precipice of the hill, ſcarce fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to a charge on horſe-backe, and there hee ſtayes, their firſt heate with his muſquets lying ſo low; and when the Cavallery did beginne to wheele about, they were ſhrewdly galled with our muſquettiers.</p>
            <p>VVhen the enemy had thus charged our men with great numbers, the laſt ruſhed forward ſo violently vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the firſt, that neyther o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them was able to rejoyne their troupes together, where by many in that diſorder were kil<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, and the hill filled with dead men and horſes.</p>
            <p>Colonell <hi>Muſtchampe</hi> who did lye vppon the one ſide of this path-way, did much miſchiefe to the enemy, by beating them in flanque with his muſquettiers: So that there was ſuch a faintnes and dejection of ſpirits amongſt them, that the Lanciers did throw downe to the ground, three of their Cornets at the feete of our ſouldiers, and baſely did forſake them.</p>
            <p>Afterward, all was in diſorder in the enemies Campe, neyther (as it was there after knowne) could they reſolue what courſe to take. The Infantecy did altogether quite their trenches and fo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts, lying againſt the Towne without any reſolution to adventure further.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the King of <hi>Poland</hi> diſpairing to be able any longer to defend the Hill, Forts, or his Campe; and being
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2631:7"/>
zealous that his Cannon might be in ſome hazard to bee loſt, if he ſhould giue any further time to approach nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer him; and ſeeing our men fortifying themſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ues vppon the great Dike, whereby hee m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght perceiue they were reſolved to go on.</p>
            <p>Vpon the 14. of <hi>September,</hi> the Ea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le of <hi>Torne</hi> comes to the King with three Regiments of <hi>Germaine</hi> foot, which had ſerved in <hi>Live-land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Army being reinforced with this new ſupply, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r with a Regiment of <hi>Swedens,</hi> vnder the Conduct of Colonell <hi>Kodwin,</hi> a bridge being layd over the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>z<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l,</hi> not farre from our Campe; and a ſtrong Fort b<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ded at the end of the bridge, where there was a competent gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon placed, to ſecure the paſſage vnto the Iſland for the ſouldiers, and the victualls of the Campe, which were left behind: The King vppon the 19. of <hi>September</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodgeth, and encampeth neere the enemy, about 300 paces from the place which the enemy ha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> kept ſtrongly fortified betwixt the Campes. Our King did reſolue that hee had gayned enough that day, to haue put his new campe in defence, by making the great Dike leſſe paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, framing it after the manner of a rolling Trench, whereby the great banke and new trench being encloſed, the King might aſwell be leſſe ſubject to any ſuddaine ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize or aſſault of the enemy, as more able to put his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined reſolutions in execution by aſſailing the enemy, with the more ſecurity of his owne men.</p>
            <p>The King ſends the Earle of <hi>Torne</hi> with 400 <hi>Germaine</hi> Muſquettiers, to the end he <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>ld poſſeſſe and make good that part of the Dike, which did ſtreach it ſelfe from the Campe to the hill.</p>
            <p>He ſends Colonell <hi>Muſtchampe</hi> with 300. <hi>Sweden</hi> foot for the defence of the Towne of <hi>Groenhoffe,</hi> which did lye aboue the Campe, over againſt the plaine field. The enemy (ſeeing vs in campe ſo neere them) drawes his whole forces vpon the hill, he plants his artillery, and played vpon our men, but all in vaine, the bullets ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther over-flying the Campe, as being ſhot from an high
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2631:7"/>
hill or did fall ſhort and beat vpon the great Dike, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any hurt done.</p>
            <p>In end, the enemy ſends forth a great number of <hi>Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſackes,</hi>
Lanc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers, and <hi>Germaine</hi> troupes of horſe, with his whole Infanttry from the hill, intending thereby not onely to beate the Count of <hi>Torne</hi> from the great barke, but alſo Colonell <hi>Muſtchampe</hi> from the defence of <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enho<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> and there after to giue a generall aſſault vppon our quarter: But every wher<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their labour was loſt by the courage of our ſouldiers, defending themſelues valiantly and preſſing vppon the enemy with much animoſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty and reſolution.</p>
            <p>Our Artillery in lik<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> manner, which was planted <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eere the trench, did ſo beate vpon the enemy, that the plaine field lying over agai<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt the Dike, was ſpread over with dead men and horſes: At length towards night, the <hi>Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> did with-draw himſelfe to his trenches on the hill: The day following was quiet and nothing attempted on eythe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſide.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur King (having buil<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed fiue forts) made himſelfe maſter of the great Dike and playne fielde, and did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his paſſage to the h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, where the enemies was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenched, to the end hee might ſtoppe the enemies ſallies from the hill, whereby they might giue any annoyance to his Camp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. The enemies in like manner (that he might more freely domineer with his Canon along the plaine field, and be more firmely fortified againſt all our enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes; and alſo that bee might be longer able to hold out the hill) did erect two forts, one vppon the right hand of the way, the other on the left hand: In the one hee plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 3 peeces of great Ordnance<hi>:</hi> in the other, ſome leſſer peeces, whereby he might ſtop our comming vp the Hill.</p>
            <p>The 21. <hi>September,</hi> our King conſulteth with his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Warre, how the enemy might be beaten from the hill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and how a paſſage might bee opened towards the Towne: And ſeeing his Campe (aſwell by ſcituation as induſtry) defenſible, and ſafe againſt all hoſtill invaſion; and (the ſallies of the enemies being cut off)<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:2631:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to the foote of the h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll was not very dangerous: Hee lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth his Marſhall of the field, with the greateſt part of the Army in the Campe; and goeth in perſon, entring the Wood with one Regiment and a halfe of foote, ſome troupes of horſe, and 1500 choyce muſquettiers.</p>
            <p>Hee layeth the foote and horſe troupe, in ambuſcade a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the trees, that they might bee as ſafe from the voll<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of the enemies ſhot, holding the top and length of the hill, where diuers fortes were erected with fielde peeces in them, as that they might bee ready to receiue and repell the enemy, if our men employed in ſervice ſhould be beaten backe from thence.</p>
            <p>Hee thought it not ſafe to ſtay any longer, but did cauſe to draw out his Ordnance, with a great deale of difficulty and confuſed haſt. He did giue order to burne the Village where hee had beene intrenched and fortified vppon the hill. Our ſouldiers did enter the trenches and forts. The King and Prince of <hi>Poland</hi> looking vppon them. Our King was vppon the hill, and would haue willingly (in the confuſed d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtraction of the enemy) haue attempted vppon the Artillery; but finding that the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage were too ſtraight, that hee could not (to the terrour of the enemy) charge them with his front inlarged; and finding the enemy vnpe<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed with bagage, betwixt the trenches and the campe: the hill being forſaken, the forts in his owne power: three of the enemies Comets left as pledges of their confuſion; and aboue all the Towne and Caſtle of <hi>Mewe</hi> relieued, which was the cauſe of this expedition. The King did reſolue hee had gayned honor enough for that day; and that the way was prepared to inforce the enemy to abandon his Campe, if hee ſhould ſtay longer: Therefore he thought it not fit (the paſſages not beeing fully knowne, betwixt the trenches and the Campe) to expoſe a certayne Victory in the valour of his ſouldiers to an vncertayne event.</p>
            <p>The enemy being perplexed what to do, keepes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe cloſe within his Campe. To forſake it, it was to flye away, which was ſhamefull. To remaine longer, he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2631:8"/>
could expect nothing but further miſchiefe: Becauſe our Army (commaunded the hill) could beate them out of their Campe onely with our Ordnance. The enemy paſſed over that night with great aſtoniſhment, ſtanding in order of battle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> expecting that our Army ſhould haue fallen vppon their Campe, as it was after-wards knowne by ſome Priſoners: At length about the firſt VVatch of the night, they ſent away their bagage.</p>
            <p>The King himſelfe by the dawning of the day, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches away with gr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at ſilence, without ſigne of Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, Drum, or phipher.</p>
            <p>The Troupes were ſeene by our Sentinells at the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery of <hi>Weul<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> lying a mile and a halfe from our Campe.</p>
            <p>Th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King of <hi>Poland</hi> had left ſome <hi>Coſſackes</hi> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue if our men ſhould attempt any thing vppon their confuſed retreate: And afterwards (when they ſhould vnderſtand that the King was any thing advanced in his journey) they had order to burne their quarter.</p>
            <p>This was the iſſue of the beſiedged and relieued towne of <hi>Mewe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our King knowing that the enemy was gone, entred the Towne and Caſtle, extolling the conſtancy, fidelity, and merit of the Souldiers, and the inhabitants with much prayſe, thankes-giving and revvard, and preſently did giue order, that a day of publicke thankes-giving to God, ſhould bee ſolemnely kept for this Victory.</p>
            <p>Thereafter hee changed the Garriſon with freſh ſouldiers, and furniſhed the Caſtle and Towne with munition and Victualls, and ſtayed in his Campe ſome few dayes, vntill hee might diſcover whether the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my vvould bend his courſe, or vvhat hee vvould attempt further.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2631:9"/>
In theſe three dayes <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rvice, there was killed of ours about 30. The loſſe of the enemy cannot bee certainely related, by common fame and diſcourſe, with ſome priſoners, there is aboue 500. killed and many wounded, who are ſent to the further parts of <hi>Spruce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is credible that the loſſe hath beene g<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eater, ſince it is not very probable that the King would haue abandoned the ſi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dge of a little Towne ſca<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe well fortified, with ſo much dim<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nution of his owne h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nour, and that of the <hi>Polonian</hi> Nobility, vnleſſe the loſſe had bin greater.</p>
            <p>Heere it muſt alſo bee remembred, that the enemy had caſt a bridge over the River of <hi>Wizel</hi> a halfe mile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue <hi>Mewe,</hi> whereby the inroades vppon the Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Stum</hi> and <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rnenbourg</hi> might bee leſſe difficult. And that the <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lonian</hi> Souldiers, who ranged vp and downe through the Biſhopricke of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lormditt</hi> might haue free paſſage to the Campe.</p>
            <p>The enemy had committed the charge of this bridg<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (which was made o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Shippes that carried Corne vp and downe the River) to 300. <hi>Coſſackes.</hi> But after th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Army (whether by neglect or feare) the b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge was abandoned: The K<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng did ſend a Cap<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayne with ſome Muſquettiers, who <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue brought away the Ships with all their furniture and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, whereof the Army hath made very good vſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2631:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
